Guide to Jack McCaine NASA papers, 1963-1994, bulk dates 1964-1979 MS 045
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Jack McCaine NASA papers
1963-1994
1964-1979
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
McCaine, Jack, 1923-
MS 045
7 Linear Feet
Photographs, correspondence, maps, charts, and memorabilia collected by McCaine while employed at Project Manager for the Army Corps of Engineers during the construction of the Manned Space Center (Johnson Space Center), 1962-1964 and while working with NASA, 1964-1979.
Biographical Note
Jack McCaine was born in 1923 in Houston. He attended Texas A&M College prior to WWII and graduated in 1950 from the University of Houston with a Bachelor of Science degree in Architecture.
He joined the Spacecraft Center Area Office, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers in 1962. From August 1962 - January 1966, Jack McCaine was employed as project manager for the design and construction of the Mission Control Center, Buildings 30 and 48, and an addition to the Central Heating and Cooling Plant, Building 24 at the Manned Spacecraft Center. This project had an extremely tight schedule, being tied to the space program in progress. This was a first--no one had built a Mission Control Center before. He was project manager for design of Project Engineering Facility, Building 45, which is a seven-story office building. He was also manager for design of Test Operations Support Facility, Building 32A. This was an addition to the large vacuum chamber building.
In addition to the above, he handled specification-writing chores for the Area Office, plus various small projects.
From January 1966 to June 1975, he was an architect, with the Engineering Division, Manned Spacecraft Center, which became the Johnson Space Center in 1973.
Some of the projects that he was responsible for include the design of Engineering Building 17, which is a two-story office building, the design of Systems Integration and Mockup Facility, Building 9a. This is the facility (a large, air conditioned hanger) that contained the full-scale mockup of the Shuttle which visitors were allowed to visit. The West end of the facility contained a large air-bearing floor that was a first-of-its-kind.
Jack McCaine was also Project Manager for various projects such as a proposed addition to Emergency Power Building 48. While in his position, he was responsible for facility preparations for Presidential visits, astronaut returns and other events.
He also handled facility modifications for various exhibits, the museum area of Building 2 and updated and maintained construction guide specifications for JSC.
From June 1975 to December 1979, he served as a General Engineer in the Engineering Division, Nasa, Johnson Space Center. In this capacity, he was Manager of the Construction Services Contract. This contract provided day-to-day, on-site services for modifications to buildings and facilities. This included a work order system handling all types of construction tasks and employing 40 to 60 craftsmen plus superintendents, estimating and accounting support. This effort provided construction services for a wide range of tasks and normally had 200+ tasks in the system at one time.
Scope and Contents
The Jack McCaine Collection consists of approximately 6.75 linear feet of newspapers, books, magazines, brochures, posters, photographs, certificates, charts, memorabilia, awards and recognitions. There is also approximately .25 linear feet in the vault.
Since most of the material covers the decade of the sixties, when the Space Center was called the Manned Spacecraft Center (the name changing to the Johnson Space Center in 1973), the early name will be used throughout the collection.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Acqusistion Information
The collection was a gift from Jack McCaine to the Woodson Research Center at Rice University on October 15, 1991 with addendums received in 1999, 2000, and 2001.
Arrangement
This material is arranged in the following series:
Missing Title
Series I: Publications, 1968-1994; 2.25 cu. ft. Boxes 1 - 4-a
Series II: Public Affairs, 1965-1974; 0.5 cu. ft. Box 5
Series III: General Photographs, 1963-1969; 0.75 cu. ft. Box 6
Series IV: Construction of the Manned Spacecraft Center, 1963-1982; 0.5 cu. ft. Box 7
Series V: Awards and Presentations, 1969-1979; 0 .75 cu. ft. Box 8 and Vault
Series VI: Memorabilia, 1969-1979; 0 .25 cu. ft. Box 9 and Vault
Series VII: Oversize, n. d.; 1.75 cu. ft. Box 10 and Drawer 34
Index Terms
Subjects
Architects -- Texas
Document Types
posters; corrrespondence; photographs; charts (graphic documents); clippings (information artifacts); awards; certificates
Places
United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration
- Series I: Publications, 1968-1994, 255529
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of newspapers, newsletters, books, and magazines.
  The Roundup, later known as the Space News Roundup and the Personnel Newsletter are newspapers; published for the personnel at the Manned Spacecraft Center. Nasa Activities consist of monthly Nasa highlights and is distributed to all Nasa personnel.
  The Publications series is organized first according to subject and then chronologically.
  - Newspapers, 255545
    - Roundup, 1968-1974; 255564 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Roundup, 1975-1977; 255563 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Roundup, 1978-1980; 255562 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Space News Roundup, 1981; 255561 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Space News Roundup, 1982; 255560 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Space News Roundup, 1983; 255559 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Space News Roundup, 1984; 255558 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Space News Roundup, 1985; 255557 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Space News Roundup, 1986; 255556 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Space News Roundup, 1987; 255555 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Space News Roundup, 1988; 255554 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Space News Roundup, 1989; 255553 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Space News Roundup, 1990; 255552 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Space News Roundup, 1991; 255551 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Space News Roundup, 1992; 255550 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Space News Roundup, 1993 (Jan-June); 255549 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Space News Roundup, 1993 (July-December); 255548 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Space News Roundup, 1994; 255547 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Rockwell International News, n. d.; 255546 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, 255538
    - Nasa Activities, 1970-1975; 255544 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Nasa Activities, 1976-1978; 255543 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Nasa Activities, 1979, 1989, 1990; 255542 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Personnel Newsletter, 1983-1987; 255541 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Inner View, 1993; 255540 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Various Titles, 1973-1974, 1992; 255539 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Books and Magazines, 255530
    - Space: The New Frontier, 1967; 255537 (Box 4A, Folder 1)
    - Earth Resources Program, 1970; 255536 (Box 4A, Folder 2)
    - Apollo II Mission Report, 1971; 255535 (Box 4A, Folder 3)
    - Apollo 17, at Taurus Littrow, 1973; 255534 (Box 4A, Folder 4)
    - Space Shuttle, 1976; 255533 (Box 4A, Folder 5)
    - Final Frontier, 1989; 255532 (Box 4A, Folder 6)
    - The First Lunar Landing, 255531 (Box 4A, Folder 7)
- Series III: General Photographs, 1963-1969, 255506
  Both color and black and white photographs can be found in the General Photographs series. Some of the more interesting photographs are ones taken of the exterior and interior, before and after renovation of the Lunar Planetary building, (originally the Jim West mansion,) which is adjacent to the Johnson Spacecraft Center.
  Also located in this series is a photograph album containing serial photos taken of the Manned Spacecraft Center during different phases of construction. The photos have been removed from the album and placed in acid free sleeves.
  - MSC Personnel and Buildings, 255509
    - Autographed Photos of Seven Original Astronauts, n. d.; 255528 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Lunar and Planetary Building (Exterior), 255527 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Lunar and Planetary Building (Interior, before Renovation), 255526 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Lunar and Planetary Building (Interior, after Renovation), 255525 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Aerial View of Manned Space Center JSC, 1963-1964; 255524 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Construction Bldg. #8, 1964; 255523 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Construction Bldg. #9A, n. d.; 255522 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Construction Bldg. #13, 1964; 255521 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Construction Bldg. #24, 1964; 255520 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Construction Bldg. #30, 1963; 255519 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Construction Bldg. #222, n. d.; 255518 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Construction Bldg. #223, 1965; 255517 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Construction of Tank, n. d.; 255516 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Apollo 7 Liftoff and Earth/Sky View, 1968; 255515 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Apollo 8 Earth/Moon View, 1968-69; 255514 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Apollo 9 LM Viewed from CSM, 1969; 255513 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Apollo 10 View of Moon, 1969; 255512 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 255511 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Negatives, 255510 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Photo Album (transferred to acid free sleeves), 255507
    - Manned Spacecraft Center, 255508 (Box 6A, Folder 1)
      General note
      See Boxes 5 and 10 for Additional Photos
- Series II: Public Affairs, 1965-1974, 255491
  Public Affairs has an assortment of interesting material used generally for publicity purposes such as the Presentation Packets, and autographed photographs of the Original Seven Astronauts. The Fact Sheets consist of pertinent information on individual Gemini and Apollo flights.
  - Publicity Material, 255492
    - Brochures, 255505 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Fact Sheets (Apollo), 1965; 255504 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Fact Sheet (Apollo 7 Spacecraft), n. d.; 255503 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Fact Sheets (Gemini), 1965-66; 255502 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Presentation Material, 255501 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Press Packets - Various Contractors, 255500 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Posters, 255499 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Program - Apollo 11 Extravaganza, 1969; 255498 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Publicity Photos, Spacecrafts and Views from Space, 1965-1966, 1968-1969, 1973, n. d.; 255497 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Publicity Photos, Astronauts, 1972, 1974, n. d.; 255496 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Autographed Photos of Astronauts, n. d.; 255495 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - NASA Facts, n. d.; 255494 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - JIPC Forms, 255493 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Construction of Manned Spacecraft Center, 1963-1982, 255479
  An inventory list of the financial costs for construction of various buildings at the manned Spacecraft Center and a list of Corps of Engineer Contracts can be found in this series.
  - General Information, 255480
    - Manned Spacecraft Center Inventory Detail List, 1971; 255490 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Corps of Engineers Contracts, n. d.; 255489 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Photograph and Drawing of Mock-up and Integration Laboratory, 1972-1973; 255488 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Summary Information on MSC, n. d.; 255487 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Basis for Design for Additions to Building No. 48, 1963; 255486 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Contract for Technical Services Facility, 1964; 255485 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Assembly and Dismantling Instructions Horn and Shroud Assembly Contract, 1965; 255484 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Architectural Drawing, Bldg. 17, 1982; 255483 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Architectural Drawing, Temporary Facilities for Mobile Quarantine Facility (MQF) Reception, 1969; 255482 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Designs (various) of Building 9A, 1972-1973; 255481 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      See Boxes 6, 6A and Box 10 for Photos of MSC
- Series V: Awards and Presentations, 1969-1979, 255457
  Some of the most interesting material in the collection can be found in the Awards and Recognition series. Jack McCaine received many awards and recognitions during his years of working on the constriction of the Manned Spacecraft Center. Among the more interesting ones are the letters received from President Richard Nixon and Frank Borman, thanking him for his contributions to the space program.
  A piece of the heat shield from "Auora Seven" (the Mercury flight of Scott Carpenter in May of 1962), along with some interesting medallions and group achievement awards can also be found in this series.
  - Correspondence, Certificates, Medallions, Jewelry and Plaque, 255458
    - Jack McCaine from Frank Borman, 1969; 255478 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Jack McCaine from Red Cavaney, 1974; 255477 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Jack McCaine from President Nixon, (see Archivist for Original), 1974; 255476 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Mrs. Jack McCaine from Robert R. Gilruth (with Memento of Lunar Landing), 1969; 255475 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - ASTP Award with Apollo 11 Medallion, 1975; 255474 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - ALT Award, 255473 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Group Achievement Award, Lunar Landing Team, 1973; 255472 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Group Achievement Award, Lyndon B. Johnson Space Center, 1974; 255471 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Apollo Achievement Award, 1969; 255470 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Group Achievement Award, Administration Directorate, 1969; 255469 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Group Achievement Award, Manned Spacecraft Center, 1969; 255468 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Skylab Achievement Award, 1974; 255467 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Skylab Operations Support Team Award, 1973; 255466 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Skylab Award, with Medallion, 1973; 255465 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Apollo 8 Plaque, with Medallion, 255464 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Apollo 11 Commemorative Certificate, 1979; 255463 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Heat Shield from Aurora Seven, 255462 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - In Vault:, 255459 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Cuff Links, Tie Tacs and Pins, 255461 (Box 8, Folder 12)
        (see Archivist)
      - Medallion from First Lunar Landing, 255460 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Series VI: Memorabilia, 1969-1979, 255445
  Items collected by Jack McCaine during the years of his association with the Manned Spacecraft Center can be found in his series. An assortment of flags representing various countries, along with a collection of patches commemorating different flights, are among the interesting items in this series.
  - Paper and Realia, 255446
    - Telephone Directories (MSC), 1969-1979; 255456 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Dedication of the LBJ Space Center, 1973; 255455 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 255454 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 255453 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Ashtray, 1969; 255452 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Realia:, 255447 (Box 9a, Folder -)
      - Flags (Foreign), 255451
      - Badges, 255450
      - Patches (Commemorative), 255449
      - Pins, White House and Apollo II, 255448
- Series VII: Oversize, n. d., 255399
  The material in this series is a mixture of various items found in some of the other series, but which will not fit into the standard size boxes.
  There is also an interesting assortment of charts, such as an Apollo Earth Orbit charts, and Atlas of Mars and Skylab 4 Mission chart.
  Although there is a General Photograph series, photos that were generated for publicity purposes can be found in the Public Affairs series. The Oversize series was formed to hold material that will not fit into standard size archival boxes. Additional photos and memorabilia can be found in the Oversize series.
  Some of the oversize items have been placed in Map Case Drawer 34. These items have been listed within the appropriate series.
  Series & Sub Series Summary
  The collection is divided into seven series, with sub-series as necessary.
  - Loose Photographs, Posters and Brochures, 255438
    - Publicity Photographs, 255444 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Brochure, Space Shuttle, The Journey Continues, 255443 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Posters, Skylab (2), 255442 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Poster, Shuttle (NASA Facts), 255441 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - In Map Case Drawer 34:, 255439
      - Photos of Moon Surface (2), 255440 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Construction Material, 255431
    - Specifications Binder - Building 9A (Systems Integration and Mockup Laboratory), March 1973; 255437 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Architectural Drawings (One Half Size) - Building 9A, 255436 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Architectural Drawings (One Half Size) - Building 17, 255435 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - In Map Case Drawer 34:, 255433 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Rendering - Space Propulsion Facility, Plumb Brook Station Matted Rendering (copy): Manned Spacecraft Center-Integrated Mission Control Center, 255434 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Box of slides, 255432 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Bldg 1, 30, 45 & ??? MSC of Central Plant & Water Tower, Unidentified
  - Charts and Maps, 255400
    - Atlas of Mars, 255430 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Gemini Mission 9, April 1966; 255429 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Apollo Mission 8, 255426 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - AEO (Apollo Earth Orbit Chart), December 1968; 255428 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - ALO (Apollo Lunar Orbit Chart), December 1968; 255427 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Apollo Mission 9, 255424 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - AEO, January 1969; 255425 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Apollo Mission 10, 255420 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - AEO, May 1969; 255423 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - ALO, May 18, 1969; 255422 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - ALO, May 23, 1969; 255421 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Apollo Mission 11, 255418 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - AEO, July 1969; 255419 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Apollo 14, 255415 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - AEO, January 1971; 255417 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - ALO, January 1971; 255416 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Apollo 15, 255411 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Lunar Orbital Science Flight Chart, July 1971; 255414 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Lunar Orbital Science Contingency Flight Chart, July 1971; 255413 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - CSM/LM Orbit Monitor, July 1971; 255412 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Skylab Mission Chart, 255408 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - SL1/SL 3, May and July 1973; 255410 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - SL4, November 1973; 255409 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - In Map Case Drawer 34:, 255401 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Translunar/Transearth Trajectory Plotting Charts for:, 255403 (Box 11, Folder 9)
        - Apollo 11, July 1969; 255407 (Box 11, Folder 9)
        - Apollo 14, January 1971; 255406 (Box 11, Folder 9)
        - Apollo 15, July, 1971; 255405 (Box 11, Folder 9)
        - Apollo 16, April 1972; 255404 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Matted Illustration of Moon Location of Sites, 255402 (Box 11, Folder 9)